<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain path-way opened to the simple-hearted for the answering all doubts and objections which do arise in them against the light and truth in the inward-parts, by which many are kept from obedience and so from peace to their panting souls / by Stephen Crisp.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17002255</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17002255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1612:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain path-way opened to the simple-hearted for the answering all doubts and objections which do arise in them against the light and truth in the inward-parts, by which many are kept from obedience and so from peace to their panting souls / by Stephen Crisp.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105706:1"/>
            <p>A Plain Path-way OPENED TO THE SIMPLE-HEARTED, FOR THE Anſwering all Doubts and Objections which do ariſe in them againſt the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> in the <hi>Inward-Parts;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY WHICH Many are kept from <hi>Obedience,</hi> and ſo from <hi>Peace</hi> to their PANTING SOULS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Stephen Criſp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1668</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105706:2"/>
            <head>A Plain Path-way Opened, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends and People,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have had a deep exerciſe upon my ſpirit concerning many who are come to feel ſomething ſtirring and moving in their hearts (that is good) to bring them into a ſerious conſideration of their courſe of life, and the inward ſtate of their Immortal Souls; and when you have ſometimes begun to turn your minds to this good thing that ſtirred in you, then have many doubts and objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ariſen in you, leſt you ſhould be miſ-led, deceived, or deluded; and leſt this thing that inwardly ſtrives with you ſhould lead you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Eronious way of the Quakers, (as the Worlds Teachers calls it) for they ſpeak, and write of, and bear a conſtant Teſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imony to ſomething that is in man, that calls upon him to repent, and to turn to the Lord; and under this very notion that ye have heard evil, and thought evil of that People; by the ſame rule you are apt to think evil of that which works in your own boſom to lead you out of Sin and Iniquity; and ſo ye are tempted to ſlight it, and to get ſome ſlighty name for it, to call it by, which Antichriſts Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſters have many to afford you; as to call it, A Natural Light; A Common Gift of the Spirit, but not a Saving Gift; Conviction of a Natural Conſcience; A Legal Work; yea, and many calls it, The Devils work to diſturb the Soul of its Peace; and ſome, A Diabolical Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thus when thou art brought to ſlight that good Principle (that ſtrives with thee) under ſome ſuch name, thou gets eaſe again, for a little while, and takes liberty to act againſt it, and to do and ſay that which this Principle doth in ſecret condemn; and then it riſeth again, and breaks thy peace, and brings trouble and anguiſh upon thy Soul? and then up comes many doubts on the one hand, and doubts on the other hand, and thy poor Soul is beſet and encompaſſed with doubts, and fears, and jealouſies; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thou fears thou withſtands the Truth to thy own deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſometimes fears again its a deluſion, and thou ſhalt be deceived; and beſides thou finds many Learned men, and worldly-wiſe men,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105706:2"/>that tell thee, that there is nothing good in thee; and here thou art in a great ſtrait, and labours under many ſorowfull thoughts, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doubtfull diſputations ariſeth in thy mind; the Fleſh now ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warreth againſt that which comes to diſturb it, and the Spirit ſtrongly warreth againſt that which reſiſts and rebels againſt it, and theſe two are contrary, &amp; theſe contrary things are both in thee, and thou poor Creature muſt feel the ſtrugling of them both; &amp; by reaſon of thy darkneſs, and doubts, and fears, thou ſcarce knows (or at leaſt with certainty) which is right: now, in this ſtate and condition, how acceptable would a Meſſenger be, one of a thouſand, to ſhew unto ſuch a one that hwich might deliver his Soul from going down into the pit, and ſave his live from the Deſtroyer; (<hi>Job</hi> 33.23.) And truly very many are in this ſtraitned ſtate in theſe dayes; for whoſe ſakes I am drawn into a deep exerciſe many times, by day, and by night, and my cry to God is, that his glorious Power may more and more ariſe to open theſe doors that are ſhut and folded upon many ſuch, and to bring forth the impriſoned ſpirits out of the Priſon-houſe, and out of the Bondage of this Spiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord was and is crucified Spiritually; and that he may expel the clouds of darkneſs, in which the fears, and doubts, and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ariſeth; and that he may make a clear way in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſuch for his Light to break forth out of obſcurity, in which the Anſwer to thoſe Doubts and Queſtions doth ariſe.</p>
            <p>And by that ſame ſpirit that labours with you, am I moved to ſend this forth unto you all, as a word of Exhortation and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in the Name and fear of the Lord God, by which as many as do rightly receive it, and make a true uſe and proof of it, ſhall find help and benefit; and ſhall know the mouth of the Queſtioner ſtopped, and the Anſwer of Peace witneſſed to their Immortal Souls, in the Lords due time. And therefore, conſider this, <hi>That every good and perfect gift cometh from above, from the Father of Lights and Spirits,</hi> who would not the death of a Sinner, but rather that he ſhould turn and live; and therefore hath he out of his infinite love, and tender mercies to the Sons of Men, prepared a way to draw nigh unto them, even while they are in their Sins, which he doth not but thorow Jeſus Chriſt, the Mediator of the New-Covenant, whom he hath freely given to be a Light unto the dark World; and that he ſhould <hi>Englighten every one that cometh into the World,</hi> Joh. 1.9.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105706:3"/>of which number thou art one, whoever thou art, and art enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt, though thou be yet darkneſs in thy ſelf, as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> once were; yet the Light ſhineth in thy darkneſs, or elſe there would not be two contrary Natures and Seeds found working in thee as there is; and this Light wherewith thou art enlightened is the the <hi>Life of Jeſus,</hi> Joh. 1.4. which he hath given a Ranſom for man; and that was not Natural, as ſome fooliſhly imagine: for if it were Natural, it could not be a Ranſom for man out of Sin; for the Sin to be Natural, and that which reproves it Natural, is contrary to the Apoſtle, who ſaid, they two that warred in the Creature were contrary; and called the one <hi>Fleſh,</hi> or Natural; and the other <hi>Spirit,</hi> or Spiritual; and Chriſt Jeſus called that which ſhould Reprove the World of Sin, <hi>The Spirit of Truth;</hi> and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt and his Miniſters calls it, <hi>A Natural inſufficient Light,</hi> &amp;c. But know this, thou that art enquiring, that that in thee which doth make manifeſt things to thee that are reproveable, that's the Light wherewith Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened thee withal, as the Apoſtle of Chriſt ſaid in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> chap. 5. v. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14. and that Principle which leads thee to do or ſay ſuch things as thou art ſecretly reproved for in thine own Conſcience, that is the Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Enemy of thy Souls Peace, which, who walks in, doth not know whither he goeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for this doth miniſter a peace and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to thee, and a delight to thy carnal mind for a ſeaſon; yet the other, to wit, the Light, the Reprover hath power to take away peace from thee again, and to judge thee, and to make that which was ſweet to thee to become bitter; and the darkneſs, nor luſt nor vanity of thy mind cannot deliver thee from this ſtroke.</p>
            <p>Now, that thou might be reſolved in ſuch a ſtate what to do, conſider, thou that haſt theſe ſtruglings in thee about the Light in thy Conſcience, whether it is true or no, or whether thou ſhalt own it or no, and art thinking in thy ſelf what is beſt for thee to do; whether to go on ſtoutly againſt it, or to ſubmit to it: I ſay, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if thou rebel againſt it, thou can never know whether it would lead thee; as it was ſaid of old, <hi>Job</hi> 24. <hi>They that rebel againſt the Light, they know not the Way of it;</hi> ſo that if thou doſt take that courſe to rebel, that will but increaſe thy ignorance of the Way that the Light leads in, and makes it more terrible to thee every time it doth appear in thee, till thou comeſt to that ſtate ſpoken of,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105706:3"/>
               <hi>Job</hi> 24.17. <hi>That the dawning of the Day will be as the ſhadow of death;</hi> for the more thou rebels againſt it, the more dark thou wilt daily grow, and ſo the leſs able to reſolve thy ſelf in thoſe doubtfull things that fill thy mind; but as darkneſs increaſeth in thee, ſo the power of it will bind thee down, as a Chain, and ſmother every good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in thee; and thus by rebellion againſt the Light, do ſome men loſe the very ſence and knowledge of it, and grows paſt feeling, and ſtrangers to it, though it be in them; for the cuſtom of Sin taketh away the ſence and the feeling of the burthen of it; but to you I write that are not yet come to this ſtate of hardneſs of heart, but are brought daily into a ſence of the burthen of Sin; and that are ready to ſay, if you were but ſure that were the Truth and way of God which ſhews you your Sin, you would follow it, and love it, and own it, but are kept off by doubts and queſtionings: Verily, I ſay unto you, before theſe doubts be reſolved you muſt try this, as, to your ſorrow you have tried the other, before you can be effectually informed; for Arguments will not do ſufficienly in this caſe; therefore try and prove what this Principle can do for thee, when thou obeyſt it, which ye know hath power to condemn you, and break your Peace when you diſobey it: Why ſhould ye always be ſhut up in unbelief, and in doubts, and ſo kept from trying and proving the Light, as well as ye have proved the Darkneſs, that ſo ye might reap the fruit of it to Salvation, as well as you have done the fruit of the other unto Condemnation? Oh, dear people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, ye cannot obey this Light of Chriſt Jeſus in your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but by taking up a daily Croſs to your own Wills, Luſts and Affections, for that is contrary thereunto; and that which leads to obey your Luſts, leads to diſobey the Light; and that which leads to obey the Light, that croſſeth the Luſts and vile Affections, which are at enmity with the Light, and muſt by it be judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; and that which leads thee to ſlight it, and call it by ſome ſlighty name, that's alſo an Enemy to it, and muſt be judged by it; and ſo, as the Light comes to rule over thoſe things in thee, which are enemies to it, thou wilt know that it will lead thee contrary to thy corrupt nature; and as thou feeleſt the thing ſo in thy ſelf, thou wilt come to be wiſer then thoſe Teachers that have called it a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light; for that which is Natural leadeth according to Nature, but that which is Spiritual, leadeth according to the Spirit, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105706:4"/>Apoſtle ſaid was contrary to the Fleſh, and warred againſt it; and ſo that objection will, by thy obeying the Light, come to be anſwered, far better then words and arguments could have anſwered it; and ſo likewiſe the ſufficiency of the Light thou wilt come to feel, if thou doſt not oppoſe it, but give up to be guided by it; and wilt know that it is able to deliver thee when thou art tempted, as weil as to judge thee when thou haſt yeelded to the Tempter: for thou knowſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that it is able to condemn thee when thou ſinneſt againſt it; but thou cannot certainly know it ſufficient to give peace, and to juſtifie, till thou obeyeſt it: So then, the plain Path-way to the anſwering thy doubts about the Principle of Truth in the Inward-parts, is, by obeying of it, and yeelding to it; for they that do evil they grow into hatred againſt it, and it judges them; as they deny to obey the Light, ſo the Light denies to juſtifie them, and ſo coming juſtly under the condemnation of it, by reaſon of tranſgreſſion they grow afraid of it: But alas, this doth but prove that it is ſent of God, for it doth Gods work, which is righteous; <hi>For to juſtifie the Wicked, and to condemn the Righteous, both theſe are an abomination to the Lord;</hi> and ſo is it with his Witneſs in thy own Conſcience, which God hath placed there to bear witneſs for him concerning all thy actions whether they are good or evil; and thou thy ſelf, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art, whether high or low, rich or poor, profeſſor or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ſhalt confeſs unto this, that this hath never condemned thee for that which was good, nor born witneſs againſt thee for that thou waſt not guilty of.</p>
            <p>And therefore all you that have been hurried and toſſed with doubts and queſtionings about the Truth, come hearken to the Counſel of God, at this time once more ſounded forth unto you from his Spirit, by a Servant of his without you, and anſwered by the meaſure of his good Spirit within you, which hath the ſame voice and cry in you, for Obedience to what is made manifeſt of God in you; obey the Light, and ye ſhall ſee daily more of it, till it break forth as a morning unto thee, and till it ſhines unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day; yea, a day of gladneſs and rejoycing to thy poor diſtreſſed Soul.</p>
            <p>Oh, Ariſe thou that ſits ſorrowing, and thou that art crying out in ſecret, becauſe of the bonds and fetters that are yet upon thee: Ariſe, ariſe, I ſay in the Name of the Lord God of <hi>Sion,</hi> who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105706:4"/>draws nigh to thee by his quickning Spirit, and hearken to his voice, who ſaith to the Priſoner, <hi>Come forth;</hi> and to the bowed down. <hi>Ariſe;</hi> and to the feeble ones, <hi>Put on ſtrength, and follow me; I will confound your Foes, and break the ſtrength of your Enemies, as I have done for my People, who have forſaken all to follow me, and obey me, ſo will I do for you: and if ye in uprightneſs walk before me, and keep my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as they have done, no power or ſtrength of the Enemy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or without ſhall be too hard for you.</hi> And when the Lord doth thus ariſe in your Souls, and ſtir up his own pure Witneſs, and his Arm awakens in you, and his pure Light breaks forth; oh, what conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is it to you, and how have many of you ſeen your vain doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings expelled, and a cleer convincement hath prevailed upon your ſpirits concerning the way of God; and at ſuch a time you have begun to reſolve to follow the Lord in his pure Way of Holineſs, thus opened unto you in the Light, though to the loſs of all; and though it be to the bearing your part of the great reproach that lies upon them that loves him more then their lives; and at ſuch a time there was felt a ſecret joy in a hidden ground in your Souls, and the ſeed of the Kingdom that had been long buried up, began to ſpring up in you, in which Seed your Souls felt ſome touchings of that Heavenly Life and Joy, which for the time exceeded all things that this World could afford; and whenſoever ye come to feel this refreſhing dew upon your Souls, then take heed and wait ſingly in the ſence of it, keep your eye to the joy that is now ſet before you in Chriſt Jeſus, the Seed; for if you let your mind; wander, and your eyes gad abroad, there be objects on every hand to lead you out from your Souls beloved, and to bring you to defile your hearts, and make your ſelves an unfit place of reſidence for him who is holy and pure, and will not dwell, nor take delight in a polluted Temple; but will withdraw himſelf, as he did from <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and from their Temple, when it was polluted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned: And beſides, when your minds are taken hold of by any of the corruptable things in this changable World, there will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently kindle a deſiring, longing, and luſting after the enjoyment of thoſe things, though contrary to the will of God; and then next the Reaſoner and Conſulter gets up in thee, and ſtarts a queſtion: May not I enjoy the Lord and this? May not I keep in the Way of Truth, and yet do this or that thing which my heart deſireth? And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105706:5"/>though it be not perfectly according to the Truth made manifeſt in me; yet I will have my will, my luſt, my deſire ſatisfied but this one time, and that's not much, ſaith the Conſulter; and this is but a ſmall matter, there be others that do greater things then this; and ſuch like reaſonings enters the mind, and this grieves and vexeth that good and righteous tender Spirit that moved in thee, and brings a weight and oppreſſion upon the pure in thee, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws it ſelf again from thee, in which thy Light did ariſe unto thee, and ſo a night comes upon thee; for where the Serpent can bring any to make a queſtion of obeying the Truth, he is as ready to frame an Anſwer, as to beget the Queſtion; but his anſwer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes comes with a Liberty and perſwaſion to diſobey, as it did by <hi>Eve</hi> in the beginning; and when tranſgreſſion is finiſhed, then death enters upon thee with its dark power, and manifold ſorrows peirceth thy poor ſoul; though the fruit was deſirable to be eaten, yet now it is eaten, thou cannot come at li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to eat of that too, though thou defireſt it; but art driven out, and kept out <hi>with a flaming ſword that turns every way againſt thee:</hi> And heres now a ground laid for doubts and queſtioning of a higher nature then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ariſe in thee; for before thou doubted of the Truth it ſelf, whether it were the Truth, but now having taſted of it, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a convincement of it, and yet let forth thy mind from it after other Lovers, and thy ears after the voice of the Adultereſs, and ſo cauſed the pure Light to withdraw from thee, thorow thy rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: now thou deſireſt thou might but ſee again what thou haſt ſeen, and feel again what thou haſt felt, but doubts and fears that thou ſhalt never ſee, nor feel, nor enjoy the like again: and now thou wiſheſt, oh, that thou hadſt ſtood in the croſs to thy own will, and that thou hadſt denied thy ſelf, that thou might not thus have loſt the ſight and ſence of thy Souls Beloved. And now thou ſeeſt, by wofull experience, whence doubts, and fears, and ſorrows do ariſe, even thy joyming with the Enemy, who brings forth reaſons againſt the obedience to the Light: And therefore now hearken to that which remains in thee, though darkneſs and ſorrow doth encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs thee; yet there is ſomething remains, which gives thee a ſence of thy ſtate and condition, and makes thee to know thy loſs and want, hear the voice of this, and this will humble thee, and bring thee into true brokenneſs of heart, and contriteneſs of ſpirit; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105706:5"/>as thou comes to know that ſtate, then thou haſt ſomething to offer to the Lord of his own preparing, which will be far more acceptable to him then a multitude of words and performances and duties, (ſo called;) and as thou in the true lowlineſs of mind doſt come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and offers up this offering, God will hear in Heaven, and will anſwer the cry of the poor and needy Soul that cannot be ſatisfied without his preſence; and he will remember his mercies of old (which never fail) for his ſeed ſake which is not yet brought forth in thee: And when God doth again ſhine forth unto thee, and make his Power known, thou muſt expect it muſt be in judgment, becauſe of the tranſgreſſion thou haſt gone into, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that in thee which led thee into the Sin, from his pure Law, which is Light, for <hi>Zion is redeemed by judgment:</hi> And therefore take heed leſt thou be offended at his appearance; take heed that thou limit not the Holy One; but if his appearance be with more ſharpneſs and bitterneſs to the carnal part then before, it is but juſt it ſhould be ſo, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what he will.</hi> he ſees more cauſe now then before, by how much more thou haſt ſinned againſt his goodneſs; but bow to his Judgments, <hi>Bear his Indignation,</hi> (as <hi>Micah</hi> ſaid) <hi>becauſe thou haſt ſinned againſt-them,</hi> Mic 7.9. And as thou yeeds to his righteous Judgement, thou wilt know the coming to the midſt of them in which <hi>the mercy is remembred</hi> and made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt; and therefore the haſty and impatient, that flees the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſoon as it begins a little to appear in them, they never find the true deliverance, but gets eaſe another way, which laſteth but for a moment; but they who comes to know a thorow work wrought in their Earth, and the Floor thorowly purged, they come to know the true and laſting Peace to their Immortal Souls; and although this is not obtained by eaſe and liberty to the carnal mind, which muſt die, yet the end Crowns all that holds out to it, they are the ſaved ones, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.13. and they find the return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſhaves, as the Prophet ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6. <hi>They that ſow in Tears ſhall reap in Joy: They went forth</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>with weeping, and bearing precious Seed, but they ſhall return with joy, and bring their Sheaves:</hi> And as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>They that forſake father and mother, wife and children, houſe or lands, yea, or their own lives f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r my ſake, ſhall have an hundred fold in this time, and in the World to come Life
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105706:6"/>Everlaſting:</hi> Forſaking and Self-denial hath alwayes been the way to Life, and to true Bleſſedneſs, and is the way unto this day. And therefore all you who have wandered in your own ways, and have not yet learned to deny your ſelves of what is contrary to the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in your Conſciences, but have deſires, and that ſtrong ones too, to keep and hold that ſtill which the Light in you doth reprove, and yet have deſires of Life and Peace too; and ſo are in many doubts and ſtraits about theſe things; to you all this is the Counſel of the Lord, and the cry of his pure Spirit; Come out of the Babyloniſh confuſion of your own thoughts, and touch not that which is unclean, and the Lord will receive you; and what God by his pure Spirit hath called unclean, let no man preſume to call clean, and to joyn to it, leſt they be found fighting againſt God, and nouriſhing, and keeping that alive which God hath appointed to die and be deſtroyed; ye cannot ſerve two Maſters, nor pertake of the Table of the Lord and the Table of Devils. Oh, feed not that birth that hungers after evil things, and delights in them; but what is for famine, let it be famiſhed; and what is for the Sword, let the two edged Sword that goeth out of the mouth of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true Witneſs cut it down, (<hi>Rev.</hi> 1.16. and 3.14.) and ſo thou may ſee the Giants in the Land ſlain before thee by one that is mighty to deliver, and to bring thee out of this Spiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> with a high hand: but this thou cannot come to witneſs, but by diligent following him, and if thou willingly yeelds to his gentle drawings when thou feelſt them in thy heart, thou wilt find them to he effectual and profitable to thy Soul, and the more thou follows him, the more thou wilt feel his goodneſs break in upon thee for thy encouragement, and the leſs thou wilt doubt of his love and mercy in leading thee ſtill farther, even unto the end, and unto that Reſt which will ſatisfie thy Soul.</p>
            <p>Therefore lay aſide all Conſultations that are againſt thy Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Gift of God in thy heart, which reproves Sin in thee; and give not way to vain and needleſs doubts about it, but as thou findſt that thou haſt been condemned and judged in thy diſobeying of it; now try and prove whether by taking up thy daily croſs, and obeying of it in thy words and actions, and in all things, if thou doſt not find the anſwer of ſweet peace and joy; and when thou ſhalt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105706:6"/>find it ſo, then will there be no more room for doubts and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt thy obeying of it; but as any queſtions or doubts doth ariſe in thee, or ſhall be caſt in thy way by any without thee, thou wilt feel the anſwer of it in thy ſelf to thy refreſhing, and ſo thou wilt come to witneſs the effectual opperation of it daily in thy Soul to work thy change and tranſlation out of thy ſelf into it ſelf, and ſo thou wilt come not only to know the Light in thee; for that one may do and periſh, (<hi>For this is the Condemnation, that Light is come, and not loved</hi>) but thou wilt know that thou art in the Light, and walkeſt there with God, and in the holy Fellowſhip, where thou feelſt the Lord near thee in his Light, and his Reward is with him: and ſo coming to walk and dwell in the Light, thy converſation is now in Heaven, as the Saints of old was, and thy unity is witneſſed <hi>with the Father and the Son,</hi> as theirs was, who ſaid, <hi>If we walk in the Light as he is in the Light, they had fellowſhip with him; and if any ſaid they had fellowſhip, and walked in Darkneſs</hi> (which all Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners do, for Sin is the work of it) <hi>ſuch,</hi> they ſaid, <hi>were Lyars:</hi> And ſuch as walks in the Light, as he is in the Light, ſuch comes to know the Blood that cleanſeth and waſheth from the Sin, and from all unrighteouſneſs; and ſuch as feels this work wrought in them are brought into ſuch a knowledge of the blood of Chriſt, that they need not doubt about it, nor have no occaſion to raiſe a queſtion, where it is, or what it is, nor what the efficacy of it is; for having the work and witneſs of the Blood in them, this forthwith reſolves all doubts that would ariſe; and ſo likewiſe thoſe that comes to know the Light in all things to be their Guide to lead out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Sin, and Imperfections, and to bring into the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Blameleſs Converſation which becometh Saints, and ſo come to know their footſteps directed before the Lord, ſuch have done doubting and queſtioning about Perfection; for ſuch ſees that which is perfect to be come, and they from the belief which they have of attaining it, are labouring to conform themſelves unto that rule, and endeavouring after it not as the carnal Profeſſors, (who ſay they labour after a Conqueſt over their Sins, with a belief they ſhall never attain it while they live;) but they ſo run that they may attain, and have the true hope in them, which they that have, are purifying themſelves as he is pure, that is their hope, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105706:7"/>
               <hi>He that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf as God is pure,</hi> that ſo, <hi>Even as he was in this preſent World, ſo they may be alſo:</hi> and ſo here the Subſtance will come, and will cauſe the ſhadow to flee, and will anſwer all thy Doubts and Queſtions far beyond what Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can do.</p>
            <p>And again, the many doubts and diſputations that have ariſen about the Reſurrection, as thou comeſt to be faithfull in the daily Croſs, that doth ſlay and crucifie that nature in thee that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted the Truth, and held the Seed in bondage; as that comes to die, and to be bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed down in the true Baptiſm into Chriſts Death, thou wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t feel the Pure to ſpring up in thee, and thou wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t be made a partaker of the new Life, and the true Reſurrection, which is Chriſt, and all that are in him are in the Reſurrection, and in the Life; for he ſaid, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the Life, he that believeth on me, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh he were dead. yet ſhall he live;</hi> and this living to God, in the Spirit of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n, is the firſt Reſurrection, which whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever comes to witneſs, the ſecond death hath no power over them, but they come to know the thing as it is in Jeſus, and their doubts are all anſwered about that alſo; for he that knows a death and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect on af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er this manner, <hi>To be dead to Sin, and to be riſen with Chriſt Jeſus in the new Life,</hi> even while they are in this earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernancle, before it is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſolv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, ſuch will never queſtion their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at the Judgment Seat of God after it is diſſolved, but do believe it with joy and gladneſs; and hath a fervent hope concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reſurrection of the dead, and have their expectation unto God in that matter, that he will, according to his Promiſe, raiſe them up at the laſt day, and will give unto every Seed his own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, even as pleaſeth him; and the Creature is not carefull then about ſuch fooliſh queſtions and doubts, as to enquire what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of body God will give them, but leaves it to the Lord in full faith that he will raiſe them up, according to the Scriptures: and ſo here all thy doubts will flee away, and are anſwered with that that was before them, as it comes to rule in the Creature, and Death that is the root and ground of them comes to be ſwallowed up in the Victory of the Life.</p>
            <p>And ſo, as thou ſeels thy part in this Reſurrection, all the doubts and fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs of thy own condition will he anſwered effectually, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105706:7"/>cannot otherwiſe be anſwered, but by that good Spirit of God that ſtrives with thee, which, when it doth prevail with thee, and thou becomes ſubject to it, then it witneſſeth for thee; for that there is a ſtate in which there is a danger of falling away, thy daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teacheth thee to thy ſorrow; and beſides, Chriſt ſaid. <hi>Every Branch in me that beareth not fruit muſt be cut off;</hi> and the many examples in Scripture of them that departed from the Faith, and made ſhipwrack of it, and turned with the Dog to the vomit, and the Sow to the mire, doth ſufficiently prove it; and if thou doſt ſtand, it is by Faith, and thou muſt take heed, and ſo mayſt thou come to the Crown, and Seal, and Aſſurance, and an Eſtabliſhment in the Kingdom, where thou ſhalt no more go forth, but ſhall have thy Souls deſire anſwered.</p>
            <p>And when thou comeſt to know this ſtate, and to receive this White Stone that hath the Name within, thou wilt then be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt or fear, given up in the will of God to do and to ſuffer all things, according to his bleſſed will: and here is the true and perfect Reſt to thy Soul whoever thou art, that art now labouring in the Iron Furnace of thy own thoughts and doubts, in the which the more thou giveſt thy ſelf up thereto, the darker thou art, and the fuller of doubts; for they will beget and multiply one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the more thou reaſons againſt obeying Gods Witneſs in thy heart, the leſs able thou art to obey it, but the little ſtrength which God gives thee, thou confults it away, and then when thou wouldſt be ſtrong thou becom'ſt feeble; and when thou wouldſt in ſome meaſure obey, thy own conſultations ſtands in the way, and hinders thee; and the more thou increaſeſt in knowledge in this ſtate, the more thou increaſeſt thy ſorrow and condemnation; ſo that ſometimes thou art ready to wiſh thou had never known ſo much of Truth; and ſometimes wiſhes thou knew more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a Point, or ſuch a Doctrine, or ſuch a Scripture, or ſuch a Myſtery, and art apt to think, becauſe thou art yet igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in ſome things relating to Truth, therefore thou art the more excuſable if thou be diſobedient: but all, poor ſoul, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the way to know more is to be obedient to a little v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch thou haſt received, and then that miſt and fog of thy own u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thfulneſs will vaniſh away from before the eye of thy mind, for it is that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105706:8"/>which hinders good things from thee, and mak'ſt thee go daily with a burthen upon thy ſhoulders, and a guilt upon thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and thou canſt not, in no caſe of thy neceſſities, come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord with an open face, but art covered ſtill with thine own iniquities; and in this ſtate thou knoweſt neither Sabbath, nor new Moon, nor Holy-day to the Lord; but all labour, toyl and travel, and weariſomneſs of ſpirit, till many even comes to wiſh an end of their dayes, and yet are in great fear that the end will be worſe too. Oh, how my Soul pitties you whoſe ſtate this is, and I have a great ſympathy with your ſorrows, and in bowels of tender love am I drawn forth to reach out a hand to help you, as one that hath obtained mercy to know deliverances, and to witneſs the way of it, and have the teſtimony of God in my heart to witneſs forth the coming of the Saviour to the poor and needy Souls, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of them, and comforting of them; and my Souls deſire is, that your bonds might be broken, and your Souls might eſcape; but this I ſay, in the Name of the Lord, to you all, there is no way for your deliverance but your giving up in ſingle obedience to that faithfull and true Witneſs of God which ſtirs and moves in thee againſt thy ſins; and therefore wait thou to feel thy mind and will ſubjected thereunto, that thou mayſt feel thy ſelf to be one of thoſe willing people, in this the day of Gods Power; and ceaſe from thy reaſonnings againſt thy obeying the Truth, and from ſaying thou cannot, thou wants power, and when God gives thee Grace then thou wilt obey, for theſe ſayings are in vain; for though it is true none can obey the Lord but by his Grace and Power given unto them, yet he hath made his Grace, <hi>even that which bringeth Salvation, to appear unto all men,</hi> as in <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11. and it hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto thee, and in thee to whom I write, and is a Reprover in thee, and thou muſt turn to that that ſmites thee, and then thou turns to the Grace of God; for its his Grace that ſtrives with thee to lead thee out of the evil that it reproves in thee, and ſo out of the World that lies in the evil, up to God from whence the Grace cometh; for whoſoever doth give up to the drawings of the good Spirit of God that moves in them, and in obedience thereto do deny themſelves of their own wills, and luſts, and evil deſires, and pleaſures, ſuch wants not power, but feels him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105706:8"/>near them that works the willingneſs firſt, and then the deed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pleaſure, and ſo the glory comes alone to be his; and then thou knoweſt the Myſtery of the Croſs, and how it is <hi>the Power of God,</hi> which all that rejects the Croſs complains for want of: And ſo, ſo long as thou liveſt in the Croſs thou liveſt in the Power, and thy obeying is eaſie, and all things are poſſible to thee thorow it; and as long as thou art daily dying to that which is corruptible, thou feeleſt the more Life, and Joy and pleaſure in that which is Everlaſting, and thy deſires grow more and more fervent, after a full and perfect injoyment of it, in the pure unity of Spirit: And thoſe deſires growing ſtrong in thee, it grows a lighter thing to thee to part with that which hinders, though it be thy boſom ſins, thy Delilahs and Darlings, yet all muſt go for the love thou haſt to Truth; and ſuch only as have this love, and continue in it, are counted worthy to be Heirs of the Kingdom of God; for ſo long as any thing be hugged and loved beſides the Lord, if the Lord ſhould manifeſt his Love to thee, thou would play the Harlot, and abuſe his Mercies, and cleave to thy old Lovers, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old did, that was after the Fleſh: and therefore, think it not ſtrange to be brought thorow manifold tryals, that thereby thou mayſt be purged and prepared as a Bride for the true Husband Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; for there is many that deſires acquaintance with him, but are not fitted for him; they muſt be waſhed firſt, and trimmed firſt, and muſt put off the vile Raiment firſt, and muſt come to know the white Linnen put on; and while this work is doing, what need of patience and quietneſs of Spirit is there; what need of ſubjection to the workings of that holy Spirit in all things, that thou may not be ſetting limits and bounds to that which muſt bound and limit thee in all things; nor ſay in thine heart, if my trials were but ſo, or my exerciſes ſo or ſo, I could then bear them; but rather ſubmit in all things willingly to do and ſuffer, and to be tried and exerciſed, even as it pleaſe the Lord to order, or ſuffer thee to be tried; and in all his dealings ſay, with the good man, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what he will with thee;</hi> and whoſoever gives up thus to him, though he ſlay them, yet ſhall they live; though he wound them, yet he will heal them again: Therefore learn pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſtilneſs of mind, for by taking thought thou can add no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105706:9"/>thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his work: I Remember <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, who were commanded to ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſee the Salvation of God in their greateſt ſtraits, and they were a figure unto thee; and now in the Light read thy figure, and wait for the Subſtance, the true Seed, that it may bring forth peace and reſt to thy Immortal Soul, and may ſet up righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in thy Earth; which is that I travel after, on the behalf of all diſtreſſed and afflicted Souls every where, to whom I am a Friend and well-wiſher, as one knowing their trials, ſtraits, doubts and beſettings; and alſo, thorow the rich love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, do witneſs the delivering, anſwering and ſatisfying-Life made m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nifeſt and revealed in its own Eternal Light, <hi>which lighteth every man;</hi> and in true deſire that you may all know the ſame, and in diſcharge of my duty towards God and my Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have I ſent forth this word of Counſel and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and do remain in my Reſt with the Lord, being thus far clear of the Blood of all men, whether they hear or forbear; and though in Bonds for the Goſpels ſake, yet the Lords Free-man, waiting in patience and full aſſurance for <hi>Zion</hi>'s full Redemption.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſwich</hi> County-Goal <date>this 3d Moneth, 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Known by the name, <hi>Stephen Criſp.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105706:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
